

# Stevens Career Center Resume Guide

# Table of Contents

Resume Overview
Step 1: Gather your experiences
Step 2: Format the document
Step 3: Choose and order section titles
Bullet Point Writing
Step 4: Bullet Points — Craft the bullet points for each chosen experience
Step 5: Proofread and revise
Action Words

## Resume Overview

#### What is a résumé and why is it important?

A résumé is a document that helps you to market your education, experiences and skills to prospective employers. It is a reflection of you as a potential candidate and is used by recruiters to assess your suitability for a specific position. A résumé is often the first piece of information received and reviewed in the employment process and the goal of the résumé is to get you an interview. It is crucial to have a well-written, formatted résumé that highlights your most relevant experiences. On average, a recruiter or business professional will spend six seconds reviewing your résumé.

#### What makes a great résumé?

When recruiters or hiring managers are reviewing résumés, you as an individual may only get up to six seconds of their attention. Your résumé must be error free. You should strive to focus on the following elements to maximize the impression you leave on the reviewer(s) and to stand out from the rest of the candidates!

**TARGETED**: Your résumé should be targeted to the industry, employer and position. Tailor your experiences, skills and bullets to the job or position you are seeking.

**CONCISE**: Tell your story through concise but specific bullet points, avoiding fluffy or extraneous language. **SELL YOURSELF**: Employers want to know why they should hire you over any other candidate. Present your accomplishments by citing any transferrable tangible or intangible skills that you have acquired through work, academic, and extra-curricular experiences.

#### How do I get started?

There is no "perfect" résumé. However, following the steps outlined in this résumé guide, along with constant revisions, will ensure that your résumé is competitive and ready for the recruitment process. Your résumé is an evolving document and is never truly finished. Follow each step and seek guidance from the Stevens Career Center.

## Step 1: Gather your experiences

- Reflect on your experiences and make a list of companies and organizations you have been involved with, including the positions you have held. These can include clubs, non-profit organizations, full-time or part-time jobs, volunteer, leadership, research, etc.
- Rank the list in order of relevance to the position you are applying to or relevance to the industry you plan to start your career.
- Use this "master list" for future résumé revisions to remind yourself of all the experiences you can choose from in order to cater each submitted résumé to your desired position.

## Step 2: Format the document

- Limit to one page
- Have bullet points next to or underneath each experience, starting each bullet with a strong action verb (ex. facilitated, collaborated, generated)
- Use a professional font style Times New Roman, Arial, Cambria; font size should be 10-12 pts.
- Change margins to be within .5" to .6" and they should be consistent all around the page
- Maintain consistency with verb tenses, bullets, alignment, fonts, sizes, hyphens, spacing, etc.
- Use reverse chronological format to best focus on recent and relevant experiences
- Save the file as a PDF and name is LastName\_FirstName\_Résumé (i.e. Stevens\_Attila\_Résumé)
- Organize your résumé by sections: Education, Skills, Leadership Experience, Work Experience, Research Experience, Projects and Interests, etc. (These sections can change based on your experiences.)

## Step 3: Choose and order section titles

#### **EDUCATION**

This section will consist of the school name, degree title, concentration, GPA, expected graduation date, and honors, if applicable

- List your GPA if it's above a 3.0
- Awards and honors are listed within this section; keep the information timely and relevant
- 6-8 relevant courses should be listed next to coursework
- Other institutions and study-abroad experiences are also listed in this section, see the below example:

## **EDUCATION**

Stevens Institute of Technology | Hoboken, NJ

Bachelor of Engineering, Civil Engineering

**GPA**: 3.32

Expected May 2020

OR

#### **EDUCATION**

## Stevens Institute of Technology | Hoboken, NJ

Master of Engineering, Civil Engineering Bachelor of Engineering, Civil Engineering Expected May 2021 Expected May 2020

**GPA**: 3.82 | Dean's List

Honors: Presidential Scholarship

Coursework: Physics, Calculus, Engineering Graphics, Engineering Design, Introduction to Programming

## Bergen Community College | Paramus, NJ

Associates in Arts, Political Science

August 2017 – May 2018

**GPA**: 3.85

#### Deusto University | Bilbao, Spain

Study Abroad

August 2016 – December 2016

- Studied Spanish art history through an immersive field study program
- Adjusted to living with a host family for the duration of the 15-week study-abroad program

#### **SKILLS**

Skills is an inventory of your skills and interests. Qualify your level of competency for speaking languages. You do not need to state your level of competency for technical skills. This section will include computer and technical skills, languages, certifications and interests (hobbies). Some students will use this to showcase activities they were not able to include under professional or leadership experiences. When describing skill level, the following adjectives should be used:

Speaking Language: Skill levels include "conversational," "proficient" and "fluent"

#### **SKILLS**

Software: SolidWorks, Arduino, MS Office: Word, PowerPoint, Visio, Excel, Project, Vernier

Lab: Chromatography, Spectroscopy, Titration

**Programming**: C++, LabVIEW, Java

Speaking Languages: French (Proficient), Bilingual in English and Mandarin

Certifications: Bloomberg Terminal, CPR Certified

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Professional experience details job and internship experience, both paid and unpaid. Ensure that bullet points communicate how you were able to cultivate characteristics that the company may be looking for (i.e. communication skills, initiative, leadership and teamwork). You can include full-time and part-time jobs as well as jobs outside your field of interest.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

Becton Dickinson | Franklin Lakes, NJ

Research and Development Engineer Co-op

January – August 2018

- Managed data analytics using Minitab and Excel such as calculating trends over time and comparison testing
- Collaborate with senior engineers and lab technicians on Safety Lock Blood Collection Set Project in Pre-Analytical Systems Department, Biosciences Division
- Observed and analyzed product performance affected by alternate materials and new manufacturing sites

#### LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE OR ACTIVITIES

Leadership experience includes involvement with extracurricular activities, volunteer experience, e-board membership, projects, competitions, group presentations, etc.

#### LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, NI

Pinnacle Scholars Peer Mentor

June 2017 – Present

- Mentor freshman through one-on-one meetings and group meetings on college transition, academic coursework, and Pinnacle Scholars requirements
- Teach fundamentals of research such as scientific method and research writing & strategy

# PROJECT EXPERIENCE or ACADEMIC PROJECTS

This section will include class projects, independent projects or collaborations with companies.

# **ACADEMIC PROJECTS**

Stevens Institute of Technology | Hoboken, NJ

Truss Project

Fall 2016

- Designed a brass truss using LabView capable of holding 470 pounds
- Analyzed its column buckling using load ratios
- Constructed the truss with brass tubing and gusset plates

OR

## PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Stevens Institute of Technology | Hoboken, NJ

Introduction to Financial Tools Stock Competition

October 2016 – November 2016

- Engaged in a trading competition with classmates to see who could generate the most returns in nine weeks
- Used functions on both the Bloomberg Terminal and Think or Swim trading platform to analyze individual securities and execute trades
- Generated a return of 0.36% and finished the competition in 5th place

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Provide details about your role in the research projects. You may describe the research itself and results from the research. Specify the nature of the research, for example if you collected data or conducted experiments. Remember to share if the research was published or other accomplishments.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Senior Chemical Research Project, Stevens Institute of Technology | Hoboken, NJ

Research Assistant

September 2017 – May 2018

- Developed a novel two layer drug delivery system using poly(vinyl) alcohol and polycaprolactone by means of nanoprecipitation and electrospinning methods
- Nominated to present research project for MIT Innovation Expo Day
- Published research findings and summary in Journals of Material Chemistry

#### **PUBLICATIONS and PRESENTATIONS**

If you have publications, or if some of your work was in major publications and you want it to stand out, include your publication history in its own section. Cite your work by including the title of your work, the publication name, date and URL, if applicable. APA (American Psychology Association) is used to cite most social science works. MLA (Modern Language Association) is used to cite liberal arts and humanities work.

#### If you've written a book...

**MLA Format**: Last name, First name. Title of Book. Place of Publication: Publisher, Year of Publication. Medium of Publication.

**APA Format**: Author, A. A. (Year of publication). Title of work: Capital letter also for subtitle. Location: Publisher.

#### Journal or magazine publication

MLA Format: Author(s). "Title of Article." Title of Periodical Day Month Year: pages. Medium of publication. APA Format: Author, A. A., Author, B. B., & Author, C. C. (Year). Title of article. Title of Periodical, volume number (issue number), pages.

#### BEFORE publication or event

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Co-author, "Enhanced anticancer activity of drug nanoparticles formulated with β- cyclodextrin," Anti-Cancer Drugs, vol. 28, no. 3, pp. 271- 280, 2017

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

Invited to deliver speech, "Sustainable Security Research" at Stevens Innovation Expo, May 9, 2018

AFTER publication or event

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

Honglei Zhan, Tina Jagtiani, and Jun F. Liang, "Enhanced anticancer activity of drug nanoparticles formulated with β- cyclodextrin," Anti-Cancer Drugs, vol. 28, no. 3, pp. 271- 280, 2017

#### **PRESENTATIONS**

Keynote Speaker, "Sustainable Energy Research" at Stevens Innovation Expo, May 9, 2018

# **Bullet Point Writing**

## Step 4: Bullet Points — Craft the bullet points for each chosen experience

- Start each bullet with a strong action verb
- Include numbers and amounts to quantify experiences and results
- Remember to not use personal pronouns such as "I, me, our"
- Convey desired characteristics through your bullet points
- Always remember to answer three questions: WHAT, HOW and WHY

**What**? — What did you do, what actions did you take? Start bullet with strong action verb (see below list) Example:

- Performed online portfolio management
- Led research

**How?** — Mention the skills or tools you utilized to achieve the action. Specifically outline your process. Usually start this part with transition words like "by," "through," "utilizing," etc. Example:

- Performed online portfolio management using MarketWatch
- Led research on the comparison of new technologies utilizing different sensor localization techniques such as BLE, UWB, Wi-Fi, and Geomagnetic indoor positioning

**Why?** — Why did it matter, what was your impact, what results did you achieve? Report on the final outcome or goal; explain why you performed the task or action. Begin this part of the bullet with phrases such as "in order to," "to," "resulting in," "achieving," "accomplishing," etc.

#### Example:

- Performed online portfolio management using MarketWatch for students to gain hands-on experience simulating real-world investing scenarios
- Led research on the comparison of new technologies utilizing different sensor localization techniques such as BLE, UWB, Wi-Fi, and Geomagnetic indoor positioning for Real Time Localization Systems (RTLS)

Weak example: Created mini sales pitches to sell teammates on buying certain asset classes Strong example: Researched futures contracts and met with teammates daily to discuss investment strategy focusing on agriculture, energy, and metals sectors

#### **IMPORTANT POINTS**

- Spell out numbers from one to nine
- Hyphenate compound numbers from twenty-one to ninety-nine
- Do not start a bullet with a number
- Use commas for numbers with more than three digits 4,377
- Use percentages be consistent within the sentence (Increased sales by \$6 million, a 24% increase from previous year)

Assume the person reading your résumé is unfamiliar with the organization and role. Therefore, make sure you are clear and concise when crafting bullets. In your bullets, show action (transferable skills), why this project/task mattered (significance), and what was the result (quantitative or qualitative).

# Step 5: Proofread and revise

Proofread carefully for consistency issues, grammar and spelling Print on résumé paper for recruiters/interviews Visit the Stevens Career Center for sample résumés and additional guidance

What not to put on a résumé:

- Inaccurate information
- Pronouns (I, my, we, our)
- Misspelled words
- Date of birth
- Social Security number
- Pictures

# **Action Words**

# Management Skills

administered	converted	generated	managed	reorganized
analyzed	coordinated	handled	merged	replaced
appointed	decided	headed	motivated	restored
approved	delegated	hired	organized	reviewed
assigned	developed	hosted	originated	scheduled
attained	directed	improved	overhauled	streamlined
authorized	eliminated	incorporated	oversaw	strengthened
chaired	emphasized	increased	planned	supervised
considered	enforced	initiated	presided	terminated
consolidated	enhanced	inspected	prioritized	
contracted	established	instituted	produced	
controlled	executed	led	recommended	

# Communication/ Soft Skills

addressed	conveyed	expressed	mediated	reinforced
advertised	convinced	formulated	moderated	reported
arbitrated	corresponded	furnished	negotiated	resolved
arranged	debated	incorporated	observed	responded
articulated	defined	influenced	outlined	solicited
authored	described	interacted	participated	specified
clarified	developed	interpreted	persuaded	spoke
collaborated	directed	interviewed	presented	suggested
communicated	discussed	involved	promoted	summarized
composed	drafted	joined	proposed	synthesized
condensed	edited	judged	publicized	translated
conferred	elicited	lectured	reconciled	wrote
consulted	enlisted	listened	recruited	
contacted	explained	marketed	referred	

# Research Skills

analyzed	determined	formulated	invented	searched
clarified	diagnosed	gathered	investigated	solved
collected	evaluated	identified	Located	summarized
compared	examined	inspected	measured	surveyed
conducted	experimented	interpreted	organized	systematized
critiqued	explored	interviewed	researched	tested
detected	extracted			

# Technical Skills

adapted	converted	fortified	rectified	solved
assembled	debugged	installed	regulated	specialized
built	designed	maintained	remodeled	standardized
calculated	determined	operated	repaired	studied
computed	developed	overhauled	replaced	upgraded
conserved	engineered	printed	restored	utilized
constructed	fabricated	programmed		

# Teaching Skills

adapted	coordinated	explained	instilled	stimulated
advised	critiqued	facilitated	instructed	taught
clarified	developed	focused	motivated	tested
coached	enabled	guided	persuaded	trained
communicated	encouraged	individualized	set goals	transmitted
conducted	evaluated	informed	simulated	tutored

# Financial/Data Skills

administered	audited	corrected	managed	projected
adjusted	balanced	determined	marketed	reconciled
allocated	calculated	developed	measured	reduced
analyzed	computed	estimated	planned	researched
appraised	conserved	forecasted	programmed	retrieved
assessed				

# Creative Skills

acted	customized	established	integrated	photographed
adapted	designed	fashioned	introduced	planned
began	developed	formulated	invented	revised
combined	directed	founded	modeled	revitalized
conceptualized	displayed	illustrated	modified	shaped
condensed	drew	initiated	originated	solved
created	entertained	instituted	performed	

# Aiding Skills

adapted	clarified	educated	helped	resolved
advocated	coached	encouraged	insured	simplified
aided	collaborated	ensured	intervened	supplied
answered	contributed	expedited	motivated	supported
arranged	cooperated	facilitated	provided	volunteered
assessed	counseled	familiarize	referred	
assisted	demonstrated	furthered	rehabilitated	
cared for	diagnosed	guided	presented	

# Organization/Detailing Skills

approved	corresponded	maintained	purchased	set up
arranged	distributed	monitored	recorded	submitted
cataloged	executed	obtained	registered	supplied
categorized	filed	operated	reserved	standardized
charted	generated	ordered	responded	systematized
classified	implemented	organized	reviewed	updated
coded	incorporated	prepared	routed	validated
collected	inspected	processed	scheduled	verified
compiled	logged	provided	screened	

# Verbs for Accomplishments

achieved	exceeded	reduced (losses)	spearheaded	transformed
completed	improved	resolved (issues)	succeeded	won
expanded	pioneered	restored	surpassed	